ILGWU. Professional and Clerical Employees (PACE) records, 5780/151
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Professional and Clerical Employees (PACE) records
1976-1990.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/151
7 cubic feet
7 linear feet
Records
Contains chronological correspondence files and financial records of the Professional and Clerical Employees (PACE) of the ILGWU. Also included in this collection files relating to hearings before the National Labor Relations Board regarding the organization of workers of the Central Tax Bureau of Pennsylvania and the Burlington News Agency (Burlington, Vermont); these files include correspondence, transcripts of hearings, notes on visits to workers, and organizers' weekly reports.
5521562
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
August 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, August 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
Contains chronological correspondence files and financial records of the Professional and Clerical Employees (PACE) of the ILGWU. Also included in this collection files relating to hearings before the National Labor Relations Board regarding the organization of workers of the Central Tax Bureau of Pennsylvania and the Burlington News Agency (Burlington, Vermont); these files include correspondence, transcripts of hearings, notes on visits to workers, and organizers' weekly reports.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States
5521562
- Gus Tyler. Letter to Brian., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Victor Gotbaum, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Gus Tyler. Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Gus Tyler. Trouble on Fashion Avenue, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  August 1983. Document to channel 13.
- Gus Tyler. Deindustrialization of America, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  June 1982. New Leader.
- Gus Tyler. A Global Strategy for the American Economy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  October 1982. New Leader
- Gus Tyler. Governance of the International Economy., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  June 1984.
- Gus Tyler. The Work Ethic: A Union View., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  September 1982.
- Gus Tyler. "Crime Book." Chapter 1-7., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gus Tyler. "Crime Book." Chapter 8-15., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes second copy of chapter 11.
- Gus Tyler. Aspen Institute Article., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  June 1982.
- Gus Tyler. Response to Harrington's "A Path for America.", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Gus Tyler. Labor's Vatican II., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  May 1985.
- General Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Administration of Funds, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Selections Committee, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- National Scholarship Fund, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Winners and finalists
- Local Scholarship Fund, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Justice story
- GEB Scholarship Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  November 10, 1977.
- College Entrance Examination Board., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- ILGWU. History (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Scholarship Clippings., 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- National Scholarship Fund., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Gus Tyler. Speech. Plains, Georgia., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  September 8, 1976.
- Gus Tyler. Multinationals. Policy Plan for President Jimmy Carter., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  September 14, 1976.
- Local Scholarship Fund, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Scholarship Fund Convention Report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- General Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Selections Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- GEB Scholarship Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Administration of Funds, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Burlington News Agency. General. [folder 1 of 3], 1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Burlington News Agency. General. [folder 2 of 3], 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Burlington News Agency. General. [folder 3 of 3], 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Burlington News Agency. Employee Handbook., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Burlington News Agency. Employee Handbook., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  3 copies.
- Burlington News Agency. Issues. Salesmen (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Burlington News Agency. Corporate., 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Colatrella, Steven. Weekly Reports., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Torres, Noemi. Weekly Reports., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Torres, Noemi. Weekly Reports., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Torres, Noemi. Weekly Reports., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Watson, Rowena. Weekly Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Koth, Bob. Weekly Reports., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Hoffman, Ann. Expenses., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Hoffman, Ann. Expenses., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Torres, Noemi. Expenses., 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Koth, Bob. Expenses., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Watson, Rowena. Expenses., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Marcus, Hilary. Expenses., 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Powers, Joanne. Expenses., 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Colatrella, Steven. Expenses., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Membership Contact Information Cards. Vermont. (Box 3)
  3x5 index cards. Filed loose in box, no order.
- Central Tax Bureau. Clippings., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Central Tax Bureau. Company Leaflets., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Central Tax Bureau. Complaints., 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Central Tax Bureau. Contract Requests., 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Central Tax Bureau. Conversations with Lawyers., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Central Tax Bureau. Corporate Headquarters., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Central Tax Bureau. Corporate Information, 1975-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Central Tax Bureau. Expenses., 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Central Tax Bureau. Stewards Training., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Central Tax Bureau. Du Bois, PA. [folder 1 of 2], 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Central Tax Bureau. Du Bois, PA. [folder 2 of 2], 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Central Tax Bureau. Du Bois, PA. Unfair Labor Practices., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  November 27, 1989
- Central Tax Bureau. Bargaining., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Central Tax Bureau. Election Petitions., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Central Tax Bureau. General., 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Central Tax Bureau. Hot., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Central Tax Bureau. Human Resources and Profit Association. [folder 1 of 3], 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Central Tax Bureau. Human Resources and Profit Association. [folder 2 of 3], 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Central Tax Bureau. Human Resources and Profit Association. [folder 3 of 3], 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Central Tax Bureau. Employer Proposals., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  October 31, 1989.
- Central Tax Bureau. Employer Proposals., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  November 20, 1989
- Central Tax Bureau. Mediator's Proposals., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  December 4, 1989.
- Central Tax Bureau. Employer Proposals., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  January 3-4, 1990.
- Central Tax Bureau. Employer Proposals., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  January 23, 1990.
- Central Tax Bureau. Admitted Exhibits. [folder 1 of 2], 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Central Tax Bureau. Admitted Exhibits. [folder 2 of 2], 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Central Tax Bureau. Hoffman, Ann. Affidavit and Attachments., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Central Tax Bureau. Bargaining Notes., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Central Tax Bureau. Correspondence. Bonus Plan., 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Central Tax Bureau. Bruno, Arthur. Bargaining Notes, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- White, Delia., 1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Watson, Rowena., 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Tuckey, Cherie., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Torres, Noemi., 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Stanford, Catherine., 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Smith, Donna., 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Saidenberg, Jocelyn., 1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Romagosa, Frank A. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Powers, Joanne., 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Marcus, Hilary., 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Koth, Robert., 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Hoffman, Ann. Expenses., 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Hensler, Benjamin., 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Harris, Amy., 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Hamilton, Sean., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Garrett, Richard., 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Downey, Kathleen [Katie]., 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Donovan, Jennifer., 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Dombrowski, Jennifer., 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Crosby, Laura., 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Colatrella, Steven., 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Bisno, Neal., 1990 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Beutin, Sita., 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Archangelo, Melanie., 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Central Tax Bureau. Mailing List., 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Central Tax Bureau. Materials for Briefs., 1975-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Central Tax Bureau. Correspondence. Miscellaneous., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations. [folder 1 of 3], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations. [folder 2 of 3], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations. [folder 3 of 3], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations. Current. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Central Tax Bureau. Objections., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Central Tax Bureau. PACE Leaflets., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Central Tax Bureau. Penn Hills, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Central Tax Bureau. Penn Hills. Unfair Labor Practices., 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Central Tax Bureau. Penn Hills. Eiler, Julie., 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  Unfair Labor Practices.
- Central Tax Bureau. Settlement., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Central Tax Bureau. Smollinger, Linda., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Central Tax Bureau. Strategy., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Central Tax Bureau. Trial Preparation., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Central Tax Bureau. Insurance., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Central Tax Bureau. Agreements. Initialed., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Central Tax Bureau. Negotiations. Minutes., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Central Tax Bureau. Unfair Labor Practices. New Bargaining., 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Central Tax Bureau. Unfair Labor Practices. Case 6-CA-21863, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  December 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  November 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  October 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  September 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  August 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  July 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  June 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  May 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  April 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  March 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  February 1990.
- Correspondence., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  January 1990.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  December 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  November 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  October 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  September 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  August 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  July 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  June 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  May 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  April 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  March 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  February 1989.
- Correspondence., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  January 1989.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  December 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  November 1988
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  October 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  September 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  August 1988
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  July 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  June 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  May 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  April 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  March 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  February 1988.
- Correspondence., 1988 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  January 1988.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  December 1987.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  November 1987
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  October 1987.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  September 1987.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  August 1987.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  July 1987.
- Correspondence., 1987 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  June 1987.
- American Express., 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Champlain Valley Central Labor Council., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Checks Pending., 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Child Care. General., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Child Care. Vermont., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Community., 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Expenses. General., 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  July 1988 - February 1989.
- Expenses. General., 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  January - June 1988
- Expenses. General., 1987 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  August - December 1987.
- Legislation., 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Media, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Vermont Politics., 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Norwich VC, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- St. Michaels College., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Vermont and Region Targets and Union Information., 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- VOC (Volatile Organic Compounds) Workshop., 1988 (Box 8, Folder 16)